Guide to the Allen Controversy Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Allen controversy papers
1965
SC0050
Allen, Lucille A., 1906-
1.5 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Reports, interviews and correspondence concerning Lucille Allen, Stanford University Dean of Women, and the Women's Council of 1964, consisting of University of women students. Controversy centers around a May, 1964, Women's Council meeting and alleged discussion of "sexual content" of reading materials in freshman English classes.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, President's Office, 1968.
Information about Access
Restricted until Jan 1, 2040.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Lucille A. Allen was the Dean of Women from 1961-1965.
Description of the Collection
Reports, interviews and correspondence concerning Lucille Allen, Stanford University Dean of Women, and the Women's Council of 1964, consisting of University of women students. Controversy centers around a May, 1964, Women's Council meeting and alleged discussion of "sexual content" of reading materials in freshman English classes.
Access Terms
Allen, Lucille A., 1906-; Stanford University. Dean of Women.; Stanford University. Department of English.; Stanford University. Women's Council.; Interviews.; Reports.; Universities and colleges--Curricula.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - The Women's Council Meeting (reconstruction of events), 1964 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology of events (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Interview with Dean Allen, 1965 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview with Kate Bransten, 1965 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interview with Nora Crow, 1965 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interview with Vicky Ganz, 1965 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview with Chana Chiba, 1965 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Interview with Leah Kaplan, 1965 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interview with Terry Moran, 1965 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sub-committee inquiry, written statement by participants of Women's Council Meeting (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ad Hoc Committee Report drafts, 1965 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ad Hoc Committee Report drafts, 1965 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dean Allen's reply ot the Committee's report, 1965 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stanford University News Service, press releases, 1965 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stanford Daily, news article concerning Women's Council and Dean Allen, 1965 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dean Allen-President Sterling correspondence, report of sub-committee and Dean Allen's reply to report, 1965 Feb (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - President Sterling's report cocnerning Dean Allen, 1965 Feb 9 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - President Sterling's copy-Ad Hoc Committee report, 1965 Feb 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Report of the sub-committee on tenure, 1965 Feb 11 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dean Allen's request for and correspondence concerning, a terminal leave of absence (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rough notes of interview with Dean Allen, 1965 Feb 4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rough notes of interview with Dean Avery, 1965 Feb 6 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rough notes of interview with Bliss Carnochan, 1965 Feb 7 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rough notes of interview with Nora Crow, 1965 Feb 9 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rough notes of interview with Caroline Ward, 1965 Feb 5 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rough notes of interview with Marian Lieb, 1965 Feb 5 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rough notes of interview with Karen Booth, Kate Bransten, Fran McArthur, Terry Moran, and Susan Sokol (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous rough notes (Box 3, Folder 8)